I'm Jason Shoemaker at Slugfest Printmaking Workshop and I'm going to show you how to wipe a plate in intaglio printmaking.
We have our tarleton.
It's been balled up.
Good in the hand.
We have our hot plate which is slightly warm just to keep the plate hot so that you can move around.
We've got our plate and it's inked up.
Now there's a few different techniques wiping the plate.
It's going to be different for every plate that you do.
You just need to print and kind of see what the plate is doing and then keep going.
So you can scrub in the ink.
That helps even it out a little bit.
I generally like to just get in to wiping.
The idea is that it's in the wrist and keep moving in a sweeping pattern.
Always starting off the plate and ending off the plate.
So it's just a motion like this.
And you keep turning the plate as you need to.
Now we're using a pretty, already saturated tarleton.
You can see ink is getting on there.
So what you want to do is just move around to a cleaner part.
Now we're going to pull off a little more ink.
And this first waves is going to get some of the excess ink off.
Get the ink down in the crevices, move it around.
You already start to see the image coming through there.
Now we've gotten to about that point we want to switch to a less saturated tarleton.
We slowly get cleaner and cleaner with the tarletons.
This one's ready to go.
And you can see it's pulling off more ink and we're getting more of the image showing through there.
And again, just keep turning around and make sure you're starting off the plate and ending off the plate.
If you stop on the plate you actually will leave ink on there.
And you actually see some of the pattern of the tarleton.
Now we go even cleaner.
This one isn't brand new but it's clean enough to do what we need it do.
And if you need to concentrate in certain areas you want to kind of pick up the tarleton.
You can hit it with your hand if you want.
But just keep it moving.